[Music]
you'll see carol lombard and robert
montgomery together for the first time
you'll see one of the funniest comedy
situations that ever hit the screen
you'll see what happens when mr and mrs
smith discover that they were never
legally married
[Music]
welcome to another episode of foreign
correspondents deeper into hitchcock
podcast my name is michael leschick and
i'm joined as always by my co-host
sebastian smolinski hello this is the
25th episode of our podcast we are
slowly reaching the midpoint of alfred
hitchcock's filmography and we discuss
each hitchcock film
in his filmography in the chronological
order trying to add a little bit of
eastern european perspective to it
today
we have a special treat for you uh
special guest that we will introduce in
a second
uh however uh first of all let's discuss
the film briefly ourselves the film is
mr and mrs smith not to be confused with
the brangelina mr and mrs smith
and the film starts robert montgomery
and crucially carol lombard we will be
talking later in the episode with
olympia kiriakou who wrote a book
becoming carol lombard
we will be talking about the star
persona of this wonderful actress
prematurely deceased
and about this particular movie and its
place
in carl lombard cannon and in alfred
hitchcock
the first thing to know about mr and mrs
smith is
that it's a scribble comedy it's a film
that doesn't seem like a hitchcock film
at all it's a it's a pure comedy with no
no suspense elements and it fits very
nicely with the general
themes of screwballs such as the comedy
of remarriage carol lombard and robert
montgomery play a married couple who
have sudden realization or rather
discovery that they are not truly
married after all that the certificate
that they got a few years ago is not
actually valid so there's this question
whether they will remarry again and how
they will handle the information between
them because they learn about it
separately and there's a little bit of
suspense in how each of each of them
will deal with with this fresh knowledge
of actually being single will they
remarry or not the whole comedy is built
around that so uh before we talk to
olympia sebastian did you like the movie
uh i'm so so about it to be honest
but i think that the great part of
rewatching this film was
also rewatching carl lombard on screen
and
carl lombard is
magnificent as always
absolutely she's
one of the key comedians of 1930s she
played in movies such as 20th century by
howard hawks nothing sacred by william
wellman
my men got free and directed by gregory
lacava hands across the table by
mitchell lyson and many many others
unfortunately her life was tragically
cut short in a famous accident
she was only 33 when she when she um
passed away and we will talk about this
of course with olympia i was also a
little bit disappointed by this film i
remember watching it many years ago at
least 20 years ago and back then it
seemed to me very witty very funny i you
know i really enjoyed it now i think as
i became i think a little bit more
discerning in my taste for screwball i
think it's definitely one of the lesser
screwball comedies norman krasna the
screenwriter of it also wasn't the top
screenwriter of that of the time
although he he wrote many many movies
and this film
also i think and we will explore it a
little bit
more later on has a big streak of
misogyny playing
in the background i think that you know
especially the way hitchcock treats um
other women in the film but also a
little bit carol lombard especially by
stressing how much she gained weight in
between
the the fake marriage and now
by by giving us big close-ups of her
uh dress scenes you know of her dress
coming at the seams i thought okay
you probably were gaining a lot of
weight yourself at that time and you are
transferring it on to this female
character uh but i think you know he was
actually
doing that in an a little bit ungraceful
even way especially since this was his
leading
uh leading lady there there are moments
that that i enjoy still in the film but
i would say it
it's one of those lesser scribble
comedies which will forever hold the
fascination of being directed by
hitchcock because it's such a unusual
hitchcock project
probably we would have to compare it to
one of the silent films that were almost
like comedies like farmer's wife for
example but so yes it will forever
remain the single
comedy pure comedy suspense less
in hitchcock's over exactly and there is
this
paradox that for example peter
bogdanovich mentioned that if you don't
know it's a hitchcock movie you probably
won't know you know without reading the
credits but if you do know then you can
approach it from that perspective and
you can look for these signs of
hitchcock's mastery or hitchcock
signature so you know it's a
maybe it's a bit of a convoluted way of
claiming that it's another of these
authors
movies so let's explore it
now with olympia kiriakou the author of
becoming carol lombard a truly
pioneering study of this
particular and very beloved
stars
persona we will be joined by olympia via
zoom we are super excited to have you as
a scholar uh not a hitchcock scholar per
se but you know we
are also very excited that we can you
know approach his films from different
perspectives and it's i think also very
exciting that your book is so new so
fresh
it's your phd
dissertation right
yes yeah i wrote it and then i adapted
it to the book so i know it's a result
of many years of research and of many
years of being with carol lombard and
everything that was written or recorded
about her
so if you we could start by you know
talking about your story your adventure
with this book with this project um what
brought you to it and what was the most
pleasant part of it and the most
difficult one of writing a
first you know scholarly book as you as
you as you mentioned in the introduction
the first scholarly book about carol
lombard
so i've been researching and been
basically a fan of carol lombard since i
was maybe like 19 or so
when i was in my undergrad in college i
had an opportunity i got a grant from my
university to go to the library of
congress to do some research so i had
worked on a project on some of her
silent comedies with max sennett
and so i finished that project i put
carol on the back burner while i was
doing my masters and then i picked up
the project again for my phd
because i really felt that well carol
lombard's a very you know popular
screwball comedian there's been very
little written about her in terms of her
other work
and her star persona so i really wanted
to
dive into those aspects of her career
more deeply
i think the the best part was getting to
watch some as i said before some of her
silent films um a lot of these are
unfortunately an archive so they're not
necessarily accessible to you know the
average person um
but i had such an it's such an honor to
to watch some of these films and to see
the
sort of the
how her performance
um her performative abilities evolved um
and so that was really cool
i think the hardest part whenever you
write about a a
hollywood star especially from that
classical era so much of the information
about them is filtered through like the
studio publicity departments and you
know fan magazines so everything you
read about them as a person you kind of
have to think well you know
how much of this has been edited to fit
like a certain persona so always having
to keep that um that info that in mind
when dealing with
um
aspects of her career off the screen um
and her star persona her marriages for
example so and especially difficult with
someone like lombard who you know never
gave really any you know candid
interviews she didn't have a diary so
uh so it was it was challenging in that
respect but
to work through it
yeah and we get to know more about her
thanks to your research and for example
the
uh surrounding events uh behind the the
accident right you you tried to
establish the exact exact date that was
something very interesting
for me and i saw a few of her i mean
most of her scribble comedies
not
many other movies but i saw these and i
was surprised for example to discover
that you know this this accident had
such an impact in the 20s on her career
and basically yeah i think your argument
before we'll you know approach mr and
mrs smith i think your argument is very
interesting that we should
uh maybe
separate her slapstick period from her
scribble period and that's if you could
maybe say a bit about it for
those listeners who you know haven't
read your book yet
uh why do you think that's the case and
uh was it difficult to argue that you
know against many scholars who or just
commentators who you know treated as one
definitely um so for those of you who
are not familiar with carol lombard she
worked for max senate from 1927
to 1929
and then her first screwball comedy
wasn't until 1934. so you have this
fairly substantial win uh period in her
you know late silent early sound career
where she didn't make really any
comedies um certainly not anything
resembling uh screwball
at that during that period she had just
signed to paramount and they sort of
positioned her as like a glamour girl
almost she had a very refined and
sophisticated star persona
very different from uh what audiences
would have uh known in the mid to late
30s
and so for me i always found it very
curious when i when i've read scholars
argue that there's some sort of
connection between her slapstick and her
screwball work because they're because
of that um huge chunk
in her career um and
really during that time that that you
know that five-year period
uh
i think paramount really didn't know
what to do with her with her
her as a star her as a performer there
was no real indication during that
period that she was going to be a
comedian um so to make that connection
between her slapstick and her screwball
work is really i think kind of unfounded
and never mind that i don't want to go
into sort of like the technicalities of
slapstick and screwball but they are
fairly just you know different uh genres
of comedy so
um well you can definitely identify some
elements of slapstick in her later
scribble work particularly the physical
comedy they are very distinct periods of
her career um i also wanted to ask about
uh how slowly slowly approaching mr and
mrs smith because this is not a film
usually that is mentioned in the carl
lombard cannon i mean we usually think
of her work with
gregory lacava or or mitchell lyson or
ernest lubich but here there's this
unlikely connection that
alfred hitchcock actually directs a
scribble comedy he he directs
carol lombard and uh and he delivers a
film that's
probably unlike any other film that he
made
but how how do you approach this film is
it a lesser lombard film or is it a
typical lumber production of that time
how how do you where do you where would
you place it in let's say carl lombard
cannon
um i place it um
it's not necessarily as physical as her
other screwball comedies carol lombard
uh compared to some of her
contemporaries was there it was uh you
know physical comedy was a huge part of
her um of her performance so it's not
it's in a different category than let's
say like a nothing sacred where she's
very active and combative um and even
with um my man godfrey um but i think it
has still those elements of you know the
rema the remarriage uh plot of course
um it's uh it's very sophisticated type
of comedy um so i think i i categorize
it as a screwball with like a little
asterisk maybe
so why do you think she was so attracted
to hitchcock as a director why did she
think that you know that was a good idea
to invite him because that's the that's
the regular story about this film right
that she wanted to work with hitchcock
and he did it as a courtesy so it's not
i'm not asking what did she think but
why do you think that based on you know
her ever and and hitchcock's effort
where are these connections maybe this
where do these sensibilities meet in
your opinion
that's a good question and i think
when you watch mr mrs smith it doesn't
seem like a hitchcock film at all but i
think there are still those elements
elements of like the
the
and sort of like the witty comedy that
you do get in hitchcock's more uh you
know
the like the thrillers for example and i
think that
i i mean i can't speak for carol lombard
but i think maybe she
saw that and thought that maybe that
could be translated into like a you know
feature film and i think you know
hitchcock's reputation at that point he
was you know coming he's just in america
right and so i i assume for her it was
very
exciting to be able to work with this
you know
director that she really
hadn't uh
had very little contact with at that
point they were they were friends they
were friendly but um you know
i think for her it was probably an
exciting and new opportunity
um how do you feel about um the screen
partners of lombard i i mean my
perception and of course i you know i
only know some of her films but you know
the tone of her performance
depends very much on who is she paired
with she's quite different with
you know john barrymore in 20th century
she's very different with
frederick march and
nothing sacred so here robert montgomery
who wasn't you know the let's say the
the
true leading man of of of scribble
comedy i would say he was sort of a
second
tier uh in that in that canon how how do
you perceive her in pairing with him as
as his screen screen partner
um personally it's not my favorite
screen pairing i don't know if they
necessarily
obviously their relationship is
adversarial in the film but i don't i
still don't know if there is that much
chemistry between the two so it's hard
for me personally as a viewer to sort of
buy into their relate to the
relationship between ann and david smith
um
i don't know i think
in that respect for me personally it's
as we talked about before i it's a
scribble comedy classify it as one of
her screwball comedies but i think it's
one of the weaker ones because of that
relationship because she doesn't have
that
um
that chemistry like she does with a
william powell
um or even a frederick march
um so well
it's it's enjoyable it's not my favorite
yeah i also
think about montgomery more as a this
noir figure right
not a scribble one so i had this feeling
and i don't know if
any of you agree that
his friend that the lawyer he's working
with he needs to be even more stiff
than the robert montgomery character to
make robert montgomery at least a bit
adventurous right there is there there
has to be this juxtaposition to make him
more interesting
when he's next to lombard
absolutely i think there's like as you
said there's like a hardness to robert
montgomery's performance that i don't
know if it necessarily meshes that well
with with lombard style and then gene
rayburn he's
um obviously he's supposed to be you
know weak character he doesn't really
have a backbone and we see that
culminate in their their final scene
together but yeah i think there's
something missing even with him too i
don't know if if i was anne i don't know
if i'd really
care that much to be with either of them
neither of them are particularly um
interesting male characters
there's also this running um trope of a
hitchcock blonde throughout throughout
hitchcock's ever and you know we
the
probably the epitome of that is tippy
hedren or or kim novak um usually
hitchcock is quite punishing in in his
relationship to those characters his
and usually to the actresses as well who
played those characters
can we can we fit carol lombard into the
lineage of
hitchcock blondes is she a version of a
of a hitchcock want or is she a
different creation different creature
altogether
i think she
she definitely for me is a little bit
different and i think the relationship
that she had with him was also different
i think she sort of
took that um that relationship that he
was known for to have with his with his
actresses and kind of push back on that
for example she brought cattle to the
set and she put little name tags on each
of the cows uh one said carol lombard
once said robert montgomery once said
alfred hitchcock to
play upon his you know actors are like
cattle um
statement um she is also
the only person i believe that ever
directed his cameo so she had a little
bit of agency in that filmmaking process
so
for those of you who haven't seen the
film hitchcock comes out of david and
anne's apartment and the camera pulls
back
um and you see hitchcock walking uh down
the street carol directed that and
allegedly she kind of was you know
egging him on a little bit saying oh you
know that's terrible we got to keep
doing it again so they did like you know
20 30 takes of that just to sort of play
with him
yeah that's that's a great great
anecdote and i also uh i've read in
leonard uh jeff's book about hitchcock
you know this anecdote that they had
very good relationship on set and that
hitchcock maybe that could be something
disappointing for him but he couldn't
embarrass her you know she was and once
again we come back to the first part of
your book to the 1920s the
the flapper figure and this you know
outgoing very brave girl and she so you
know he couldn't embarrass her he coming
from this more
uh prudish or equally prudish but uh in
different sense british culture
they were like almost like equals so i
think that's also a very nice story of
uh maybe of a working relationship that
was of course cut to too fast right i
mean abruptly by the by the tragic
accident in which carol lombard died but
there are these fantasies about lombard
as a hitchcock heroine
i mean some people
fantasize what could happen later in the
40s right
yeah
oh absolutely that's one of the things
that i think about so often is
you know had her had her
she uh lived uh what her career might
have become and i often wonder what
would she have been like in like for
example a film noir or even you know a
hitchcock thriller right i think she had
the capability to
uh play those types of roles we see that
a little bit in her late career in her
late 1930s early 1940s uh career where
she transitioned from screwball to drama
and so i think that might have been a
natural progression for her so it's the
always
heartbreaking to think such a missed
opportunity professionally
yeah i always
kind kind of imagined that her career
might have taken similar
route to barbara stanwix who you know
late in career
she had those tv appearances and you
know it's such a
such a tremendous loss that that you
know that that career was cut cut short
yeah but i think also lucille ball is
like one of the inheritors of lombard
right
uh so
yes so they were actually very good
friends um and uh carol was like her
mentor
uh and a lot in lucille ball's one of
her autobiography she says that carol
allegedly came to her in a dream and
sort of encouraged her to pursue i love
lucy and you can definitely see
similarities in their comedic styles so
i can imagine that you know lombard when
she died she was 33
unfortunately hollywood
doesn't really allow women to age very
gracefully so i can imagine she would
have had to transition into perhaps
um
you know away from the leading leading
lady into something else whether it be
you know production television
um as you said following uh you know
like a barbara stanley's footsteps
transitioning into another type of role
so
it's uh it's interesting to think of the
possibilities
so probably this this line between noir
heroine and scribal heroine wasn't as
clear right and or generally between
comedy and and more serious modes uh as
barbara stanweek shows and um i wanted
to ask you you both actually about the
sexual innuendos we find in this film of
course we find them in almost every
hitchcock movie but in this case the the
story is interesting because um
many americans american critics
were kind of proud of hitchcock that he
made this very american movie which is
his first film set in new york the the
very first image is uh
you know manhattan skyline or like
you know uh big buildings in manhattan
and
he
so he could do something very american
but at the same time i would argue that
there are some british traits you know
like this for example his
uh nastiness towards female characters i
think it's something he actually brought
from from uk but my question is
does it work for you still i mean can
you sense it as this as this screwable
late actually quite a late scribble
comment the early 40s that still wants
to
play with the code in some ways does it
does is it you know something you feel
when you watch this film
absolutely i think there are
the sort of the illusions to sex are so
potent in this film um
one that stands out for me particular um
and i write about it in my book is the
very final scene where they're in the
ski lodge um and cara lombard's
character anne she's having trouble
putting on her skis and at some point
she's sort of feigning like she's uh
difficulty she can get her ski on but
she wants david to help her um and then
eventually he does and the camera
cuts to a shot of her skis sort of
crisscrossing and that's how the film
ends and so i think that's sort of like
this
allusion to sex you know what's gonna
happen next we don't have to say it
explicitly right and so
i think in that way uh where you know
you have traditional screwball comedy
the sort of physicality is that allusion
to sex in in hitchcock's in in mr mrs
smith it's that sort of
the more subtle uh visual innuendo
i mean that's just one example it's
throughout the film but uh i think
that's the most explicit
right i also think that you know this is
a rather late um screwball comment it's
it's a wartime film right it was made
during
uh during the war i think you know it
it's on the very
sort of tail end of the of this except
of course for late masterpiece which is
adam's rib but um but here i i think
that you know it's also depending on the
quality of the writing and i think that
you know the screenplay by norman krasna
is
it has its better moments and its worst
moments it's not you know the most
brilliant uh script he wrote many many
movies which were sort of like this
middle you know shelf of of of
of dialogue um and brilliance let's say
but one last question that i had
had to do also with
this particular moment in the reception
of carol lombard's career how was she
received at that particular time she was
definitely you know seen as one of those
scribble ladies in the 1930s
and then you know should play in another
wartime film which is to be or not to be
but what was what was she seen as in
1941 by the american public
so mr mrs smith is actually a very
pivotal point in that late career um in
1937 she
her contract was paramount ended and it
was at that time where she basically
said you know i'm tired of being
uh typecast as a screwball comedian i
want to move into drama so from 1939 to
1940 she made four back-to-back dramas
and unfortunately um well they were
critical successes the public didn't
really accept her in those types of
roles they kind of wanted more super
ball from carol
um and so i think the the poor box
office performances of those films
really turned her off from pursuing more
of those types of projects so mr mrs
smith
it was the last film that she made in a
three picture deal with rko
and that was her essentially her return
to comedy
and i i think
in that way it was sort of her coming
home it was a very comfortable type of
role um well it's not scribble as we
talked about before it's not screwball
in like the
my man godfrey kind of sense it was a
much more familiar type of role that uh
you know audiences
uh would have wanted to see her in and
so i think for her in that way this film
was um an enjoyable one to make
yeah and also to comment upon it uh also
in your book in the chapter about her
scribble comedies
you pursue this line that maybe there
were some
personal reverberations of this film
meaning that you know she was now
uh a wife i think right wife of clark
gable or just a um
partner they were married yes so so that
this film in a way also may mirror you
know their mature relationship right
that there's these parameters of stardom
were kind of connecting these two these
two spheres
absolutely yes
she
began dating clark gable in 1936 and
they got married in 1939
and so
by that point by 1939 to 1942 when she
died uh there was this sort of tension
between
maintaining her own i think independent
identity and then being labeled as you
know mrs clark gable and i think you get
that same sense with ann and mr mrs
smith and that you know she
still loves david i think that's quite
clear by the end of the film but she
does also like that taste of
independence and so you do see those
parallels between you know screen uh you
know screen character and you know off
screen
uh persona right they're they're really
merging in such a unique way
in this film
yeah i'm i have like one or two
questions
to wrap up slowly uh
but yeah i think
we
you know one of the
let's say aims of this of our meeting
could be to
to claim that mr and mrs smith is a
forgotten masterpiece of hitchcock and
carol lombard but apparently that's not
really the case i think
all of us has
have this more of a lukewarm approach to
this film and hitchcock conveniently
almost
went outside of the picture of our
conversation which is very fine because
you know part of of your study and of
contemporary studies of hollywood is to
the center directors right after so many
decades of them being at the center
my biggest problem with this film is
probably pacing i i just watching
mr and mrs smith and then watching
gregory la cavas or horde hoaxes movies
make it clear that
at least in this case hitchcock wasn't
up to the task when it comes to the
timing that's for me that's that's the
biggest problem i have with this film uh
but also i i cannot stop thinking that
um this
let's say perfect setup of this
marital problems
in a single apartment because apartment
plays an important role in this film was
elaborated by hitchcock later for
example in rear window so maybe that
film was you know important in certain
certain respects
uh that's more of a more of an
observation but on a more personal note
i wanted to ask you about to be or not
to be so the last carl lombard film
because
i always tell to my us friends and
polish friends generally that it's
probably the best classical hollywood
movie set in poland right so just a
simple question do you like this film i
mean
do you find it enjoyable as much as we
do
oh absolutely it's my favorite cara
lombard film and it's probably one of my
favorite comedies from the 40s i think
it's spectacular um and i think
carol fits so well into that lubitsch
world um
and i i mean i think unfortunately so
many elements of it are still so
relevant today
um i always played in uh one of my film
history classes and i'm so thrilled that
my students always
are so
into it they are so receptive of
of the film and of its comedy
it's fantastic
the last thing um do you have any other
uh book projects on your horizon because
that was a huge thing probably that you
you know
not probably it was a huge huge huge
book a very important project do you
have some
other plans professional plans now
um so i also and aside from carol i also
work a lot on disney stuff so i have
some i have a chapter coming out in the
book um next year
in terms of like a big project i think
i'm going to start tackling clark gable
in particular his politics he was
unfortunately very involved in huack
he was like one of the basically the
founding members of huak he never
testified so i think that's like an
element of his persona that needs to
really be explored
um
so we'll be looking forward to that well
thank you so much this was a real honor
and a pleasure and we are sure that this
conversation will bring you know even
more attention to to both to your book
and to carol lombard who
unfortunately passed away so early but
she you know left all those wonderful
roles so it was a real pleasure to talk
to you thank you very much for having me
i really enjoyed talking about mr mrs
smith and carol with you both thank you
so much have a wonderful
day
it was really wonderful to have olympia
as our guest i feel that the subjects
that we were talking about were very
illuminated by
by her presence so
i think we all agreed that it's not our
favorite favorite hitchcock film
um
next
episode we will discuss suspicion which
definitely has more of a suspenseful
streak we will be seeing
cary grant and will be rejoining joanne
fontaine who was already in
hitchcock's rebecca are you looking
forward to suspicion
very much very much so
mostly because
i like cary grant in this you know no
irish
style so i think i think it's gonna be a
treat and i'm very happy that i will
revisit that one with you
absolutely i'm also looking forward to
it and
we encourage you to watch it in the
meantime and
if ever anyone gives you a glass of
glowing milk don't drink it
so this was mr and mrs smith the 25th
episode of
foreign correspondents di perinto
hitchcock